<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mikoaj Modzikowski DevOps presentations</title>
    <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Mikoaj Modzikowski DevOps presentations</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/1/</guid>
      <description>How to CI/CD with Jenkins? by Mikoaj Modzikowski Jenkins - who is he ? Jenkins has started as project Hudson in 2004 at Sun Microsystem, developed by Kohsuke Kawaguchi in java Jenkins as we know has started in 2011 as Hudson fork (while Hudson name belonged to Orcale after buying Sun) and Kohsuke Kawaguchi received O&amp;rsquo;Reilly Open Source Award Features used in current Jenkins development appeared in 2014 as Jenkins 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/2/</guid>
      <description>Discarding builds Too many builds and artifacts are heavy on jenkins operating memory You can set specific number of days you want to keep builds and/or artifacts You can set specific number of builds and/or artifacts you want to keep  Jobs configuration schools Manual - of course :) DSL - Domain specific language Plugins / tools using API - for instance job-builder plugin Pipeline closures - requires initial run  DSL - Domain specific language Allows to configure jobs as Groovy scripts Available under env.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/3/</guid>
      <description>UI Lifting Green Balls plugin - replaces blue color with green introducing Western culture context Simple Theme Plugin - Allows to install out of the box skins or introduce custom CSS - https://github.com/jenkinsci/simple-theme-plugin Groovy Postbuild plugin - Codified edition of HTML in Jenkins UI  UI Lifting - Simple changes UI Lifting - Material http://afonsof.com/jenkins-material-theme/ UI Lifting - groovy extra description UI Lifting - groovy extra description - code UI Lifting - Adding icons  https://github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/4/</guid>
      <description>Parameters  Parameters are available during build for executor shell   If parameters is defined with lower case letters then it will be available in shell with UPPER_CASE name  Parameters are also available in global variable params for pipelines    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/5/</guid>
      <description>Jobs triggers Poll SCM - Jenkins actively checks source code and triggers jobs if any changes where introduced Internal - upstream/downstream relations to the other jobs (e.g. build pipeline -&amp;gt; deployment pipeline) Webhooks - generic hooks, VCS providers, Jira Jenkins Crons Syntax - TZ=UTC H 8 * * *  Triggers tricks - when conditions Triggers tricks - when conditions Triggers tricks - when conditions Triggers tricks - when conditions  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/6/</guid>
      <description>Agents types SSH Agents - connected to Jenkins via SSH connection performed from Master to Agent JNLP (Java Network Launch Protocol) Agents - connected to Jenkins via socket connection performed from Agewnt to Master Dynamic agents - they are mostly JNLP agents and they are created dynamically on Master&amp;rsquo;s request - supported bo JCloud  SSH Agents Recommended by CloudBees when using their plugin :) Has less software requirements what comes in handy when using dynamic agents Has issues with non-linux servers  JNLP Agents Comes in handy when you need to codify your Jenkins Agents (jar could be  Has less software requirements what comes in handy when using dynamic agents Has issues with non-linux servers  Kubernetes agents Under the hood the Pod object is formed within side container which contains JNLP agent Jenkins master has to be reachable from K8s cluster Pod template could be defined in Jenkins configuration with label or could be created inline  Docker software isolation Workspace could be mapped into docker container within the agent if it has docker software This requires mapping container user to user running jenkins process on agent Private registry and dockerfile are supported too  Dynamic VMs Supported clouds: Digital Ocean, GCP, AWS, Azure, etc&amp;hellip; Best settings are retention time and number of executors set to 1 It is required that VM image contains java   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/7/</guid>
      <description>Plugins management - installation Manual - from central repository or HPI file (useful for downgrades) :) Ansible - geerlingguy role for installing Jenkins Docker - https://github.com/jenkinsci/docker/blob/master/install-plugins.sh Helm Chart - template for deploying Jenkins on Kubernetes (use @ for pinning version)  Plugins management - configuration All Jenkins configurations - including plugins and jobs are XML - backup them! You can use JCasC - Jenkins Configuration as Code (tool from Praqma) Try to use Jenkins Credentials for storing secrets for plugin configurations - same as for Jobs ;)   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/99/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/jenkins/99/</guid>
      <description>sources  DSL Pipelines Jenkins Core API (for libraries) Basic steps  and all steps for pipelines   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/1/</guid>
      <description>Par s贸w o programowaniu  Mikoaj Modzikowski</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/2/</guid>
      <description>Kim jestem?  Pracuj jako programista do spraw budowy aplikacji w firmie Egnyte. Skoczyem Politechnik Poznask, prywatnie fan jazdy na rowerze, papug i gier komputerowych. </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/3/</guid>
      <description>Zawody w IT  Dev (Developer)  Frontend - warstwa wizualana Backend - warstwa logiczna Fullstack - poczenie obu   Tester - QA (Quality Assurance)  Manualny Automatyczny Procesowy   
Zawody w IT  Ops (Operations)  Administratorzy System贸w Zarzdzanie dostepami i narzedziami Wsparcie sprztowe   HR (Human Relations)  Specjalici ds. rekrutowania Zarzdzanie biurem Organizaja kultury firmy   
Zawody w IT  Administracja  Finanse Koordynacja 偶ycia w biurze Planowanie urlop贸w   Menad偶erzy  Menad偶er projektu Menad偶er Produktu Menad偶er menad偶er贸w&amp;hellip; ;)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/4/</guid>
      <description>Fakty i mity o programistach  Jest osob zamkint w sobie i cich FASZ Umie dobrze matematyk P PRAWDA Umie wama si na fejsbuka FASZ Naprawi zepsuty komputer FASZ Istniej lepi programici PRAWDA</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/5/</guid>
      <description>Jakie cechy powinien posiada programista  Umiejtno pracy w zespole Ch do nauki oraz rozwoju Znajomojzyka angielskiego Kreatywno, rozwizywanie problem贸w, zrozumienie drugiego czowieka  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/6/</guid>
      <description>Kilka ciekawostek o programistach  18% Aktywnych zawodowo programist贸w to studenci Prawie poowa programist贸w aktywnie wspiera wolne oprogramowanie 80% Programist贸w uwa偶a swoj kodowanie za swoje hobby 35% Aktywnych zawodowo programist贸w ma mniej ni偶 5 lat dowiadczenia  I 57% ma mniej ni偶 5 lat dowiadczenia w zawodzie 
Kilka ciekawostek o programistach  27% Nie uzyskao wy偶szego wyksztacenia 46% Ma wyksztacenie wy偶sze I stopnia 63% Skoczyo informatyk Pozostae popularne kierunki to: inne kierunki techniczne, administracja, chemia, biologia, fizyka, matematyka, ekonomia 86% Przyznaje 偶e wikszoci rzeczy nauczya si w domu</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/7/</guid>
      <description>Algorytmika  Nudna reguka: zadaniem algorytmu jest przeprowadzenie systemu z pewnego stanu pocztkowego do po偶danego stanu kocowego  Na chopski rozum: Jest to wymylenie i zapisanie sposobu jak doprowadzi coz punktu A do punktu B  Jest wiele rodzaj贸w algorytm贸w: zachanne, sztucznej inteligencji, genetyczne  
Algorytmika - algorytm parzenia herbaty  Nalej wody do czajnika Wstaw czajnik Przygotuj szklanke Wsad藕 torebk do szklanki Poczekaj a偶 woda si zaparzy Zalej herbate Dosyp cukru Zamieszaj Wypij</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/8/</guid>
      <description>Podstawy programowania  Wszystko numerujemy od 0, a &amp;lsquo;okrge liczby&amp;rsquo; to potgi 2  Zmienne, np: x=1, albo x=&amp;ldquo;czesc&amp;rdquo;  Warunki, np: if x==2: print(&amp;lsquo;Hello&amp;rsquo;)  
Podstawy programowania  Ptle liczce, np: for x in range(10): print(x)  Ptle warunkow, np: while(x &amp;lt; 10): print(x) and x = x + 1  Nauk zaczynamy od prostych rzeczy: tradycj jest zrobienie programu kt贸ry napisze na ekranie &amp;lsquo;hello world&amp;rsquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming/9/</guid>
      <description>Dzikuj za uwag! Czas na cz praktyczn :) online @ https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/programming Filmiki i linki dla ciekawskich:   Zbi贸r materia贸w  do nauki pythona w sieci oraz interaktywny kurs online od podstaw po polsku.   Ksi偶ki do pythona: python z minecraftem , python na start  i Laura Ipsum , odpowiednik ksi偶ki &#34;wiat Zofii&#34; w Informatyce.     Linda Lukas z Finlandii opowiada o tym jak uczy programowa  najmodszych (eng)   Thomas Suarez (12 lat) z USA opowiada o tym jak zosta programist  (eng)   Materiay do programowania z prelekcji     Film o Denisie, lepym programicie   Strona z grami do nauki programowania i algorytmiki, tynker i codecombat    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/0/</guid>
      <description>SysOps/DevOps Pozna MeetUp #5  Mikoaj Modzikowski</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/1/</guid>
      <description>root@sodo-meetup # whoami    My name is Miko, my interests are: lingustics, travels and programing  I&amp;rsquo;m going to start soon my career as a Build Automation Engineer, previously Java Developer and DevOps  
 root@sodo-meetup # uname -a    This presentations is focused on popularizing IaC approach using terraform as an example  Terraform will be broadly presented as a tool with mostly easy examples  Presentation is full of links, sources and referals so if you are interested in the topic - check out later the presentation online    root@sodo-meetup # terraform plan -out=introduction    Infrastructure as Code - short summary  Terraform features specification  HCL together with &amp;ldquo;${interpolation}&amp;rdquo;  Modules and community tools  Snippets!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/2/</guid>
      <description>IaC Approach  Wikipedia definiton:  Infrastructure as code (IaC) is the process of managing and provisioning computer data centers through machine-readable definition files, rather than physical hardware configuration or interactive configuration tools.   A good starting article about IaC from thorntech  
Pros Operations:  Infrastructure is self-documentating by its code  Configuration can become part of Continuous Configuration Automation  Keeping IaC inside VCS: changes tracking, easier rollbacks and reviewing process</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/3/</guid>
      <description>Facts about terraform  Is declarative -&amp;gt; tell what you want  Uses push configuration method  Communication is JSON based  Is extendable by plugins written in Golang   Digest of the providers set  Clouds: AWS, GCP, Azure, Alibaba, DigitalOcean, Heroku, OpenStack  Monitors: Datadog, Grafana, Icinga, New Relic, PagerDuty  Software: Docker, Nomad, Consul, Vault, Chef, Kubernetes  Networks: Cloudflare, DNS Servers, HTTP Requests  Databases, scripts, archives, vcs, many more&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/4/</guid>
      <description>HCL &amp;amp;&amp;amp; &amp;ldquo;${interpolation}&amp;rdquo;  HCL is compromise between human-friendly and machine-friendly configurations  HCL is fusion of complete programing languages and data structure languages  HCL is JSON-compatible - you can generate JSON and run it as HCL  HCL supports comments and &amp;lt;&amp;lt;EOF syntax for multiline strings.   Exact specification on the language can be found in the Hashicorps repository Data types  // vars: &amp;ldquo;${var.aws_account_number}&amp;rdquo; //(0.11) var.aws_account_number // (0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/5/</guid>
      <description>What are terraform modules  Modules are blackbox configuration in which only some set of parameters is provided in aim to create more complex infrastructure behind the scenes.  Modules usually have a set of outputs which can be referenced in your terraform file.  
Using modules  First source is official terraform registry  You can also find terraform modules on git repositories. There are plenty of them.  If you don&amp;rsquo;t feel satisfied you can always create your own modules and reference them as local files  Module is normal terraform project with: main.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform/6/</guid>
      <description>Thank you! online @ https://mlodzikowski.pl/presentations/terraform repo with snippets @ https://github.com/mkjmdski/terraform-examples Sources and helpful links to study terraform:  Jakub Jaczak article  pointing terraform cons  Alexander Savchuk post  on CCA   Pavan Belagatti&amp;rsquo;s analyze  on popularity of terraform   Two articles about terraform on AWS: provisioning AWS  by Manisha Sahasrabudhe and terraform ECS cluster  by Tom Trahan  
More helpful links   Hashicrop webinars on YT   Introduction to terraform from Gruntwork.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>